<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<crafts>
	<craft>
		<template>1</template>
		<girlName>Abigail</girlName>
		<craftTitle>Hand-Embroidered Monograms</craftTitle>
		<download>pdf/crafts/abby_monogram.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/crafts/HandEmbroideredMonogramsSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/crafts/HandEmbroideredMonogramsLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>A hand-embroidered handkerchief was a very common item in Abigail's day. It could be given to someone as a sign of affection or gratitude. You can also try embroidering some pillowcases or a t-shirt for a fun personalized item.</description>
		<items>
			<item>A word processing program</item>
			<item>A computer printer</item>
			<item>Linen, to be embroidered</item>
			<item>Tracing paper</item>
			<item>Pencils</item>
			<item>Pins</item>
			<item>Embroidery needles</item>
			<item>Scissors</item>
			<item>Embroidery floss</item>
			<item>Embroidery hoop</item>
			<item>An Iron</item>
		</items>
		<directions>Open your word processing program and type out your initials or first name. Go through the fonts on your computer and select a script-style font. You can play with different variations and sizes until you've developed a personalized monogram that suits your personality. When you've finished designing your monogram, print it out.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Using a piece of tracing paper and a pencil, carefully trace the letters of your monogram. Flip over the tracing paper and re-outline the letters, this time backwards. When finished, determine where you'd like your monogram to be on your linen. Transfer the monogram by securing the tracing paper with a pin and tracing the letters one more time. The letters should be faintly outlined on the fabric. Next, place your embroidery hoop around this area.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Choose the color of embroidery floss you wish to use and begin filling the area with satin stitches. Sew the satin stitch by bringing the needle up on one side of the outline of the first letter. Insert the needle down into the fabric directly across the outline of the letter. Point the needle down into the fabric right beside the point you brought up initially. Repeat this stitch to fill in the open spaces of each letter. Knot and cut your thread between letters. Change the color of your embroidery floss as desired.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>The satin stitch is a beautiful way to embroider a monogram but can be time consuming. If you're having trouble, you could also head to your local bookstore and pick up a beginner's guide to embroidery and follow the visual instructions.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>After you've finished satin stitching each letter, stitch an outline in either the same color embroidery floss or a contrasting one. Remove your embroidery hoop and press your design lightly with an iron.</directions>
		<source>Photo Credit: Trigga/IStockphoto</source>
	</craft>
	<craft>
		<template>2</template>
		<girlName>Abigail</girlName>
		<craftTitle>Basic Knitting</craftTitle>
		<download>pdf/crafts/abby_knitting.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/crafts/basicKnittingSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge></imageLarge>
		<description>Knitting is a great pastime and an easy - and inexpensive! Abigail would have knitted all of her sweaters, mittens, and socks to keep her warm in the winter. Lucky for you, we have the mall!</description>
		<items>
			<item>Worsted weight yarn, any color</item>
			<item>Size 8, 14" long knitting needles</item>
			<item>Yarn needle with big eye</item>
			<item>Small scissors</item>
		</items>
		<directions></directions>
		<steps>
			<step image="images/crafts/basicknitting/step1.png">Casting On<![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Make a slip knot on the shaft of one knitting needle with your yarn. This counts as your first stitch. Next, place this needle in your left hand. Hold the other knitting needle in your right hand to control the yarn. Insert the point of your right needle, from front to back, into the slip knot under the left needle.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Hold the left needle still in your left hand and move your fingers left to brace the right needle. With your right index finger, pick up the yarn from the ball. Release your right hand’s grip on the needle and use your index finger to bring the yarn under and over the point of the right needle.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Return your right fingers to the right needle and draw the yarn through the stitch with the point of the right needle. Slide the point of the left needle into the back of the new stitch, and then remove the right needle.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Pull the ball of yarn gently to make the stitch fit snuggly on the needle. You have now made one stitch (called casting on) and there are two stitches on the left needle.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Insert the point of the right needle, from front to back, into the stitch you just made then under the left needle. Repeat all of these steps 26 times, until you have 28 stitches on your left needle. This completes the cast-on row, which is the way you’ll begin any knitting project.</step>
			<step image="images/crafts/basicknitting/step2.png">Knitting Your First Row<![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Hold the needle with the stitches in your left hand; insert the point of the right needle into the first stitch, from front to back, just as if you were casting on. With your right index finger, bring yarn from the ball under over the point of the right needle. Drawn yarn through the stitch with the right needle point. Slip the loop on the left needle off, so that the new stitch is entirely on the right needle.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>This completes one knitted stitch. Repeat these steps on each stitch remaining on your left needle. When the last stitch is worked, one row of knitting is complete.  Now, you should measure your work. It should be about 7" wide; if it’s close, you’re doing great! If it’s too big, start over and cast on fewer stitches. If it’s too narrow, start over and cast on more stitches.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>When your work is the correct width, begin to knit rows as follows: Turn the right needle and hold it in your left hand. With the free needle in your right hand, work through the First Row steps in each stitch. After another row is completed, switch your needle to your left hand and repeat another row of stitches. Work rows of stitches until your block measures about 9" long.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>To complete the block, bind off the stitches.<![CDATA[<br /><br />]]></step>
			<step image="images/crafts/basicknitting/step3.png">Binding Off<![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Knit the first two stitches; insert the left needle into the stitch you knitted first and pull it over the second stitch and completely off the needle. One stitch is now bound off. Knit one more stitch, insert the left needle into the first stitch on the right needle and pull it over the new stitch and completely off the needle. Don’t work too tightly.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Repeat these steps until there is only one stitch left. Cut the yarn off the skein, leaving 6” at the end. With one of your knitting needles, draw the end up and through the last stitch to secure it. Thread the yarn end into the yarn needle and weave the end into several stitches to secure it.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]></step>
		</steps>
		<source>Photo Credit: Lana Stewart/Getty</source>
	</craft>
	<craft>
		<template>1</template>
		<girlName>Abigail</girlName>
		<craftTitle>Homemade Candles</craftTitle>
		<download>pdf/crafts/abby_candles.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/crafts/HomemadeCandlesSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/crafts/HomemadeCandlesLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>All of Abigail's candles would have been handmade, there was no scented candle shop in her day. Also, candles would have been her primary light source. Today, thankfully, we have light bulbs.</description>
		<items>
			<item>Wooden skewers or chopsticks</item>
			<item>Candle dyes</item>
			<item>Candle molds</item> 
			<item>Candle scents</item>
			<item>Candle wax</item>
			<item>Candle wicks</item>
			<item>Stove</item>
			<item>Double boiler</item> 
			<item>Pot holders</item>
			<item>Scissors</item>
			<item>Wooden spoons</item>
			<item>Old nylon stockings</item>
		</items>
		<directions>Making candles can be dangerous task. Be sure to have an adult help you with the process.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Choose your wax, mold, and wick. You can find all of these supplies at a craft store. You can add scents to your candle as well. Follow the instructions that come with the supplies you've purchased, as they will vary greatly depending upon the brand.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>After preparing your mold and wick, melt the wax in a double boiler until it reaches pouring temperature. If you don't have a double boiler, you can place a metal mixing bowl over a pot of simmering water. The pouring temperature should be specified on the packaging that comes with the candle wax. Tilt the mold and pour the wax smoothly down the sides. Fill the mold to within a couple of inches from the top. Gently tap the mold to release air bubbles in the wax.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Poke a skewer or chopstick down along the wick to release air bubbles. Watch for the candle to shrink as it cools. Top off the wax to the original level. Put the cooled candle and mold into the refrigerator for 10 minutes. Turn the mold upside down over a clean towel. The candle should slide out easily.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>If you want your candles to look really great, you can polish them with a nylon stocking. Untie the wick and trim it to 1/2 inch above the top of the candle. To even out the bottom of the candle, place it in a warm skillet and let it melt until it is level.</directions>
		<source>Photo Credit: Jonathan Kantor/Getty</source>
	</craft>
	<craft>
		<template>1</template>
		<girlName>Abigail</girlName>
		<craftTitle>Wax Seal</craftTitle>
		<download>pdf/crafts/abby_waxseal.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/crafts/WaxSealSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/crafts/WaxSealLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>A wax seal was the only way to seal a letter in Abigail's day. Today we have envelopes with glue built right in, but these wax seals give a letter an extra special touch.</description>
		<items>
			<item>A seal stamp</item>
			<item>Sealing wax sticks</item>
			<item>Paper or envelope</item>
			<item>Vegetable oil</item>
		</items>
		<directions>Gather your supplies. You can find wax sticks and seals at various specialty stores or online. Choose an appropriate seal. If you can find a brass one, use it. Brass seals do not need to be oiled and are much easier to work with. Crimson is the traditional wax color, but you can use any color you like.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>If the seal you have is not brass, no need to worry. Dab some oil onto the seal and rub it in with a paper towel. Light the wick of your wax stick so that the wax starts to heat up. Drip the molten wax onto the area you wish to seal. Drip enough wax so that it creates a pool the size of a nickel. Set your wax stick aside in a piece of tin foil.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Press the seal into the wax vertically and apply pressure evenly so that the impression is made entirely. Lift off the seal and allow the wax to cool.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Protect the seal if you're not going to be hand delivering the document or envelope. The wax can be brittle and break in the mail. Place it inside a padded envelope or deliver by hand for the best results.</directions>
		<source>Photo Credit: Chromacome/Getty</source>
	</craft>
	<craft>
		<template>2</template>
		<girlName>Piper</girlName>
		<craftTitle>Portrait Photography</craftTitle>
		<download>pdf/crafts/piper_photography.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/crafts/photographySmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge></imageLarge>
		<description>Piper would have used a Kodak Eastman film camera to take her photos. Today, we have digital cameras that save time and money. If you're feeling particularly artistic, why not ask your parents if they have a film camera lying around? You might be surprised at your results! Piper had a natural eye for photography, but not all of us are so lucky. Follow these tips and you'll be a shutterbug before you know it. </description>
		<items>
			<item>A digital camera</item>
			<item>Friends, family, or pets to photograph</item>
		</items>
		<directions></directions>		
		<steps>
			<step image="images/crafts/photography/step1.png">Start out by looking your subject in the eye.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Direct eye contact is as engaging in a picture as it is in real life. When you’re taking a picture of someone, hold the camera at the person’s eye level to unleash the power of those magnetic gazes and mesmerizing smiles. All by itself, the eye level angle will create a personal and inviting feeling that pulls you into the picture.<![CDATA[<br /><br />]]></step><source>Photo Credits:<![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>1.Pascal Genest/ iStockphoto</source>
			<step image="images/crafts/photography/step2.png">When taking photos outside, be mindful of bright sunlight.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Sunlight can create unflattering facial shadows. Get rid of the shadows by using your flash to lighten the face. Make sure you review your results on your digital camera’s screen. On cloudy days, forget the flash! Cloudy weather produces some of the most beautiful photographs. Some photographers enjoy shooting during the "golden hour" or "magic hour." This refers to the hour before sunset and the hour after sunrise. Try shooting some photos then.<![CDATA[<br /><br />]]></step><source><![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>2.Isaac Lane Koval/ iStockphoto</source>
			<step image="images/crafts/photography/step3.png">Move in close.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>If your subject is smaller than a car, take a step or two closer before taking the picture and zoom in on your subject. Up close you can reveal telling details, like a sprinkle of freckles or wise wrinkles. But don’t get too close, or your pictures will be blurry! The closest focusing distance for most cameras is about three feet, or about one step away from your camera. If you get closer than the closest focusing distance of your camera, your pictures will be blurry.</step><source><![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>3.knape/ iStockphoto</source>
			<step image="images/crafts/photography/step4.png">The middle of your picture is not the best place for your subject.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Center stage is a great place for a performer to be. However, the middle of your picture is not the best place for your subject. Bring your picture to life by simply moving your subject away from the middle of your picture. Start by playing tic-tac-toe with subject position. Imagine a tic-tac-toe grid in your viewfinder. Now, place your important subject at one of the intersections of lines.</step><source><![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>4.oleg filipchuk/ iStockphoto</source>
			<step image="images/crafts/photography/step5.png">Next to the subject, the most important part of every picture is the light.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>It affects the appearance of everything you photograph. On a great-grandmother, bright sunlight from the side can enhance wrinkles. But the soft light of a cloudy day can hold back those same wrinkles. Don’t like the light on your subject? Then move yourself or your subject.</step><source><![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>5.druvo/ iStockphoto</source>
			<step image="images/crafts/photography/step6.png">Take some vertical pictures.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Is your camera vertically challenged? It is if you never turn it sideways to take a vertical picture! All sorts of things look better in a vertical picture. So next time out, make a conscious effort to turn your camera sideways and take some vertical pictures.</step><source><![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>6.Claudia Dewald/ iStockphoto</source>
			<step image="images/crafts/photography/step7.png">Be a picture director.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Take control of your picture taking and watch your pictures dramatically improve. Become a picture director, not just a passive picture-taker. A picture director picks the location: "Everybody go outside to the backyard." A picture director adds props: "Girls, put on your pink sunglasses." A picture director arranges people: "Now move in close, and lean toward the camera." Most pictures won’t be that involved, but you get the idea: Take charge of your pictures and win your own best picture awards.</step><source><![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>7.oleg filipchuk/ iStockphoto</source>
		</steps>
		<source></source>
	</craft>
	<craft>
		<template>2</template>
		<girlName>Piper</girlName>
		<craftTitle>Paper Cranes</craftTitle>
		<download>pdf/crafts/piper_papercranes.pdf.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/crafts/paperCranesSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge></imageLarge>
		<description>Origami is the traditional Japanese art of folding paper. Practiced since the 17th century in Japan, Origami has since become a popular pastime for people all over the world. The paper crane is by far the most popular folding design.</description>
		<items>
			<item>Origami Paper</item>
			<item>Patience</item>
		</items>
		<directions></directions>
		<steps>
			<step image="images/crafts/papercrane/step1.png">Start with a square piece of paper,coloured side up.<![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Fold the top corner of the paper down to the bottom corner. Crease and open again. Then fold the paper in half sideways.</step>
			<step image="images/crafts/papercrane/step2.png">Turn the paper over to the white side.<![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Fold the paper in half, crease well and open, and then fold again in the other direction.</step>
			<step image="images/crafts/papercrane/step3.png">Using the creases you have made, bring the top 3 corners of the model down to the bottom corner. Flatten model.</step>
			<step image="images/crafts/papercrane/step4.png">Fold top triangular flaps into the centre and unfold.</step>
			<step image="images/crafts/papercrane/step5.png">Fold top of model downwards, crease well and unfold.</step>
			<step image="images/crafts/papercrane/step6.png">Open the uppermost flap of the model, bringing it upwards and pressing the sides of the model inwards at the same time.<![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Flatten down, creasing well.</step>
			<step image="images/crafts/papercrane/step7.png">Turn model over and repeat instruction #6.</step>
			<step image="images/crafts/papercrane/step8.png">Fold top flaps into the centre.</step>
			<step image="images/crafts/papercrane/step9.png">Repeat on other side, so your model looks like this.</step>
			<step image="images/crafts/papercrane/step10.png">Fold both 'legs' of model up, crease very well, then unfold.</step>
			<step image="images/crafts/papercrane/step11.png">Inside reverse fold the "legs" along the creases you just made.</step>
			<step image="images/crafts/papercrane/step12.png">Inside reverse fold one side to make a head, and finally fold down the wings.</step>
		</steps>
		<source></source>
	</craft>
	<craft>
		<template>1</template>
		<girlName>Piper</girlName>
		<craftTitle>Paper Lantern</craftTitle>
		<download>pdf/crafts/piper_paperlantern.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/crafts/PaperLanternSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/crafts/PaperLanternLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>Often associated with celebrations and festivals, paper lanterns are common in both Chinese and Japanese cultures. Use these pretty lanterns as decorations at your next party!</description>
		<items>
			<item>Balloons</item> 
			<item>Crepe paper</item> 
			<item>Battery-operated tea light candles</item> 
			<item>Large bowl</item> 
			<item>Water</item> 
			<item>Flour</item> 
			<item>Needle</item>  
			<item>Wire</item>  
			<item>Needle nose pliers</item> 
			<item>Sponge paintbrush</item> 
			<item>Sealer</item>
		</items>
		<directions>Tear your crepe paper into strips or shapes and set aside. Change up the shape and color of your crepe paper to give your lantern a unique look. Mix one part flour to three parts water into your large bowl. Stir until well blended, but still lumpy. This will be your paper mache paste.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Next, blow up and tie a balloon. This will be the shape of your lantern. Dip your crepe paper into your paper mache paste then drape it over your balloon. Continue until your balloon is almost completely covered. Leave an opening at the top of the balloon so you can reach your hand into it and put your battery-operated candle in place. Set aside to dry.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Using your foam brush, spread sealer all over your lantern once dried. Decoupage sealer works well. Make sure you add a few coats until you like the sheen.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Pop the balloon with your needle once the crepe paper has dried fully. Twist your needle into both sides of your lantern near the top. This will be where you put your wire to hang your lantern.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Cut a piece of wire with your wire cutters. Use a tape measure to measure the length from the hook that you are hanging your lantern from to where you would like your lantern to hang. Multiply that number by two and cut your wire at that length. If you wanted to hang your lantern 6 inches, you would cut 12 inches of wire.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Insert one end of the wire through the small hole that you made. Curl the end of the wire with your needle nose pliers. This will stop the wire from falling out. Repeat on the other side. Pull and bend your wire till you are satisfied with its shape. This will be how you hang your lantern. Turn on your battery operated tea light candle and insert into your lantern. Hang and enjoy.</directions>
		<source></source>
	</craft>
	<craft>
		<template>1</template>
		<girlName>Piper</girlName>
		<craftTitle>Flower Leis</craftTitle>
		<download>pdf/crafts/piper_flowerleis.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/crafts/FlowerLeisSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/crafts/FlowerLeisLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>Leis are traditionally made with orchids. Don't sweat if you can't find them, though, any flowers will do. Remember, if you're giving someone a lei always seal it with a kiss on each cheek!</description>
		<items>
			<item>Flowers</item>
			<item>Crochet thread</item>
			<item>Large-eyed needle</item>
			<item>Scissors</item>
		</items>
		<directions>Begin by cutting the stems off of your flowers. String your needle with a double length and tie a knot at the end to hold the two strands. The double length of crochet thread, on the needle, should measure 40 inches.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Poke the bottom of the flower through the center and pull it down to the knot. Continue stringing the flowers until you have nearly come to the end of the thread. Run the needle and thread through the beginning knot several times, until the hold is firm.</directions>
		<source>Photo Credit: Jennifer Daley/IStockphoto</source>
	</craft>
	<craft>
		<template>1</template>
		<girlName>Mem</girlName>
		<craftTitle>Leather Embossing</craftTitle>
		<download>pdf/crafts/mem_leatherembossing.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/crafts/LeatherEmbossingSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/crafts/LeatherEmbossingLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>	Lucky for you, we have pre-made metal templates available at stores. Mem would have spent hours creating her own template and would've paid a visit to the local blacksmith for help cutting metal.</description>
		<items>
			<item>A piece of leather</item>
			<item>Metal embossing templates</item>
			<item>Wood scraps</item>
			<item>Nails</item>
			<item>Rubber Mallet</item>
			<item>1/4 inch thick piece of Styrofoam</item>
			<item>Weights, such as heavy books or bricks</item>
			<item>An iron</item>
			<item>Rags</item>
			<item>A bowl of water</item>
		</items>
		<directions>It's important to choose soft leather to emboss. These leathers are much easier to work with throughout the process. Next, choose a template. You'll be able to find pre-made metal templates at craft stores and on the Internet.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Lay your leather out on a flat surface. Place some rags into a bowl of water and wring them out. Make sure the rags are still damp, but not dripping. Lay the rags over the piece of leather and let sit for 15 minutes.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Take your chosen metal template and place it on a small scrap of wood. Nail the edges of the template to the wood so that it will not move around. Remove the rags from your leather and decide where you want your embossed design to be. Lay that area over the template, with the front side of the leather facing down on the template, so that the back of the leather is facing upwards towards you.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Put a thin piece of Styrofoam on top of the leather. Apply your weights (either a few heavy books or a brick) and allow to sit for six hours. Do not move the books or the bricks during this time.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>After six hours, remove the weights and the Styrofoam, taking care not to move the leather. You should be able to see the leather pressed into the template, with the edges fairly pronounced. If some of the edges are still undefined, tap them firmly with a rubber mallet.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Remove the leather from the template and allow the leather to dry fully.</directions>
		<source>Photo Credit: joecicak/IStockphoto</source>
	</craft>
	<craft>
		<template>1</template>
		<girlName>Mem</girlName>
		<craftTitle>Old Paper</craftTitle>
		<download>pdf/mem_oldpaper.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/crafts/OldPaperSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/crafts/OldPaperLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>Paper was a luxury in the colonies; Mem was very lucky to have her diary to record her daily life.</description>
		<items>
			<item>Several sheets of paper</item>
			<item>2 (9" x 13") baking pans or trays</item>
			<item>Instant coffee crystals</item>
			<item>Several tea bags</item>
			<item>Paper towels</item>
		</items>
		<directions>Preheat your oven to 150 degrees. The oven will be used at the end of the aging process to dry the paper.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Use the instant coffee crystals to make a 6-ounce cup of hot coffee. Make the coffee up to four times as strong as you usually would, adding extra crystals if desired. Brew a six-ounce cup of hot tea. The finished product will be lighter or darker depending upon the strength of the tea and coffee. <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]> Pour a mixture of half coffee and half tea into the baking pan until it is about 1/4 inch deep. Reserve the remaining coffee and tea and refill as necessary. Soak the paper, one sheet at a time, in the coffee and tea mixture. Allow the paper to soak for ten minutes.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]> Carefully remove the wet paper from the pan. Lay flat on a second baking pan, soaking up any pools of liquid with paper towels. Bake the paper in the oven until dried. Keep a close eye on the paper in oven while it is drying.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]><![CDATA[<h4>For more artistic effects, try these tips:</h4>]]>Crumple up the paper into a ball and flatten it out once more. Continue to soak as usual.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Sprinkle some of the instant coffee crystals on the wet paper before baking for a spotted look. You could also open up a tea bag and sprinkle bits of the leaves on the paper for a similar effect.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Rub a dry piece of paper with a used tea bag before soaking for a feathery effect. </directions>
		<source></source>
	</craft>
	<craft>
		<template>1</template>
		<girlName>Mem</girlName>
		<craftTitle>Bead-Making</craftTitle>
		<download>pdf/crafts/mem_beadmaking.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/crafts/BeadMakingSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/crafts/BeadMakingLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>Bead making was a vital and sometimes religious activity in Native American society. The Nauset and Wampanoag tribes would have used beads as a currency; the beads were used in trade and considered very valuable.</description>
		<items>
			<item>Polymer clay</item>
			<item>Butter knife</item>
			<item>Toothpick</item>
			<item>Baking sheet</item>
			<item>Parchment paper</item>
			<item>Acrylic paint</item>
			<item>Acrylic crystal clear, shine sealer</item>
			<item>Cording or string</item>
		</items>
		<directions>Knead your polymer clay until it is soft enough to mold. Squeeze it between your palms and fingers to smooth. Stretch and squeeze the clay until it is pliable.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Roll the clay into a long, snake-like cylinder. Cut the clay cylinder into sections. Determine what size you'd like the beads to be and use the putty knife to cut them accordingly. Shape each individual bead as desired and insert a toothpick through its center to form a hole. This hole will be used to string the beads later on.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Line a baking tray with a piece of parchment paper and place the beads onto the tray. Cover the beads with another sheet of parchment paper. Check the instructions of your polymer clay and bake in an oven accordingly.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Remove the beads from the oven after they are baked and allow them to cool. Once cooled, paint them with acrylic paint and spray with a crystal clear acrylic sealer for shine. Finally, string your beads onto cording or string and tie.</directions>
		<source>Photo Credit: iinwibisono/IStockphoto</source>
	</craft>
	<craft>
		<template>1</template>
		<girlName>Mem</girlName>
		<craftTitle>Book Binding</craftTitle>
		<download>pdf/crafts/mem_bookbinding.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/crafts/BookBindingSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/crafts/BookBindingLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>Bookbinding is not an easy task! If Mem wanted to create a new journal, she would've spent hours gathering the supplies and fashioning her book. If you're feeling like creating your own journal is too difficult, you can always pick up a notebook at a variety of stores.</description>
		<items>
			<item>Heavy needle</item>
			<item>Waxed thread</item>
			<item>Awl punch</item>
			<item>Spring clips</item>
			<item>Cover Stock</item>
			<item>Paper</item>
		</items>
		<directions>Measure and cut two pieces of cover stock. The cover stock must be the same size as the pages of your book. Choose one of the pieces as a front cover.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Measure 1/2 an inch from what will be the left hand edge of the front cover. Bend the cover stock here to crease the stock so that the front cover will open easily.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>On the same piece, measure down 1/2 an inch from the top and bottom. Mark this on the cover stock with a pencil and then measure the distance between these two marks. Divide this space into equal thirds and mark. You will be punching holes through these marks and driving waxed thread through the covers and the pages to make your book.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Stack the pages of your book on top of the back cover. Now, place the front cover on the top of the stack. Tap the edges and get everything lined up nicely. Use spring clips to hold everything in place. Before punching holes through the covers, make sure that parts of your book don't slip out of place. Punch the awl through the front cover, the sheets of paper, and the back cover of your book. Be careful while using the awl punch. It is very easy to punch clear through the book and into the surface you are working on. Trying working on top of a workbench or a thick piece of Styrofoam.<![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Thread the needle and sew up your book. Start from the center holes and work toward the top and bottom edges of the book.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>This method of binding a book is best used with smaller books that have fewer pages. Make sure you have plenty of waxed thread. You'll need a decent length of thread at least three times the length of your book.</directions>
		<source>Photo Credit: Christoph Wilhelm/Getty</source>
	</craft>
	<craft>
		<template>1</template>
		<girlName>Mem</girlName>
		<craftTitle>Flowered Hair Wreaths</craftTitle>
		<download>pdf/crafts/mem_hairwreaths.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/crafts/FlowerWreathsSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/crafts/FlowerWreathsLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>We're lucky to have a wide variety of exotic and colorful flowers available for use at our local florist. Mem would have been able to use only flowers that grew around Plymouth settlement. If you're feeling particularly authentic, try using flowers that grow in your yard or neighborhood.</description>
		<items>
			<item>Drop cloth or newspapers</item>
			<item>Ribbons</item> 
			<item>Wire wreath frame</item>
			<item>Scissors</item>
			<item>Craft wire</item>
			<item>Dried flowers and foliage</item>
			<item>Extra Firm Hold Hairspray</item>
		</items>
		<directions>Lay out newspaper or a drop cloth; this is a messy job! Gather your foliage. Suggestions include magnolia, oak, cushion bush, asparagus fern, and bay laurel. Then select your dried flowers such as lavender, hydrangea, seafoam statice, and straw flowers. You want all of your flowers and foliage to be around 6 inches long; trim and cut where necessary.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Attach the craft wire to the wreath frame by bending one edge around the frame. Select several stems of the foliage and place them together in a bunch, with the ends all facing the same direction. Next, add dried flowers on top of the bundled foliage. Place the bundle onto the floral frame where the wire is connected. Hold the bundle in place and wrap the wire around the flowers and foliage as well as the frame. You will need two hands for this, one to hold the bundle, the other to wrap the wire.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Wrap the floral wire around the bundle twice, and then pull tightly. Make sure to leave the wire attached to the frame, for you have a long way to go. Gather another bunch of foliage and flowers and lay it so the leaves overlap with the first bunch and cover the cut ends. Make sure the stems on both bunches are facing in the same direction.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Continue overlapping and wiring the bunches to the frame until you complete the circle. Tuck the final bundle under the first then wrap both tightly with the excess wire. Tie a knot in the wire and clip with scissors. When finished, give the wreath a spray with the hairspray. After you spray the wreath, tie ribbons around the area where you started. Leave the ends of the ribbon long so that they hang down your back when you wear the wreath. </directions>
		<source>Photo Credit: realitybytes/IStockphoto</source>
	</craft>
	<craft>
		<template>1</template>
		<girlName>Margaret</girlName>
		<craftTitle>Cameo Necklace</craftTitle>
		<download>pdf/crafts/margaret_cameo.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/crafts/CameoNecklaceSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/crafts/CameoNecklaceLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>Cameo pendants and necklaces reached the height of their popularity during Margaret's day. Recently, they have come back into fashion and authentic antique cameos are worth quite a bit of money. Ask your parents if you can peek around the attic or your Grandma's jewelry box, you might find a priceless treasure!</description>
		<items>
			<item>Polymer clay, in two colors</item>
			<item>Cameo mold</item> 
			<item>Butter knife</item>
			<item>Cornstarch</item>
			<item>Paintbrush</item>
			<item>Oven</item>
			<item>Sandpaper, preferably fine grain</item>
			<item>Jewelry clasp</item>
			<item>Ribbon</item>
		</items>
		<directions>Select two colors of polymer clay. Ivory is the traditional color for the "face" of the cameo, while the other color will serve as the background. Dust the cameo mold (can be found at jewelry making or craft stores) with a paintbrush dipped in cornstarch. This will prevent clay from sticking to the mold.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Roll out a small piece of the background clay slightly larger than the mold. Gently press the mold into the background clay. There should be an outline of the cameo. Remove the background from the mold using the X-ACTO knife.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Take a small ball of the ivory clay and press it into the mold. Use the end of the paintbrush for precision; since this is the face of the mold we want to get every single detail. Add more clay as necessary.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Place the background clay on top of the ivory clay. Press very gently and keep the clay level. Trim any overflow.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Set your oven to 230 degrees and bake the cameo for 30 minutes. Remove from the oven and gently remove from the mold. If the edges are uneven, use a bit of sandpaper.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Using a jewelry clasp, attach your homemade cameo to a piece of ribbon to create a necklace.</directions>
		<source>Photo Credit: Sxc.hu</source>
	</craft>
	<craft>
		<template>1</template>
		<girlName>Margaret</girlName>
		<craftTitle>Pressed Flowers</craftTitle>
		<download>pdf/crafts/margaret_pressedflowers.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/crafts/PressedFlowersSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/crafts/PressedFlowersLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>Pressing flowers has been a crafty pastime for many centuries. Victorian women in particular enjoyed the activity.</description>
		<items>
			<item>Blotting notebook papers</item>
			<item>Construction or tracing paper</item>
			<item>A thick book (like the phonebook)</item>
			<item>Flower presses</item>
			<item>Fresh flowers</item>
			<item>Fresh plant materials</item>
			<item>Tweezers</item>
			<item>Old newspapers or newsprint</item>
			<item>Glue</item>
		</items>
		<directions>Select flowers, grass, moss, and a background material such as construction or tracing paper.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Gently squeeze the center of the flowers with your index finger and thumb to flatten. Thin out mosses and grasses. Use tweezers to arrange the plant material into the desired design. Try to use flowers and plants of the same thickness to avoid uneven pressure. After you've finalized your design, glue the flowers to your background.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Place the arrangement between sheets of blotting paper, and then place a piece of newspaper or newsprint on top of the blotting paper. Place fat heavy objects like a phonebook or a dictionary on top of the newspaper. Let the flower arrangement sit for two weeks under the books.</directions>
		<source>Photo Credit: agalma/IStockphoto</source>
	</craft>
	<craft>
		<template>1</template>
		<girlName>Margaret</girlName>
		<craftTitle>Host A Tea Party</craftTitle>
		<download>pdf/crafts/margaret_teaparty.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/crafts/HostingaTeaPartySmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/crafts/HostingaTeaPartyLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>Here are some ways to host your very own Victorian-style tea party. While you may not have fancy china and silver platters at your disposal, you can still recall the feeling of a Victorian tea party with these simple guidelines.</description>
		<items>
			<item>Victorian-style calling cards</item>
			<item>A tea set</item>
			<item>Plates</item>
			<item>Napkin rings</item>
			<item>Silverware</item>
			<item>Platters (plastic or silver)</item>
			<item>Lacey tablecloth and other table linens</item>
			<item>Place cards</item>
			<item>Tea (any variety)</item>
			<item>Snacks for your guests</item>
			<item>Classical or ragtime music</item>
			<item>Flowers, for decoration</item>
		</items>
		<directions><![CDATA[<h4>Inviting Your Guests</h4>]]>Create a set of Victorian-style calling cards. These will serve as your tea party invitations. You can research different formats of calling cards on the web and design your own layout. There are thousands of clip art sites that have free images of flowers and your home computer should have a few fancy script fonts for you to experiment with. Victorian tea parties typically had 8 guests, but you can invite as many or as few people as you like. Invites should always go out at least two weeks before a party.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]><![CDATA[<h4>Prepping the Table</h4>]]>Cover the table with a white tablecloth. Victorian and Edwardian women would have used an expensive tablecloth made of damask or brocade, but you can use a paper one for your party. If possible, cover your white cloth with a lace tablecloth. If you can't find a lace tablecloth, head to the fabric store and buy a few yards of lace. Your guests won't know the difference!  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Set the table with delicate china decorated with a floral pattern, polished flatware, and water goblets. Fold linen napkins and wrap them with polished silver napkin rings. Place sugar, cream and milk in fancy serving dishes. If you can't find some of these items, don't worry! Having even few of these fancy details will recall a classic Victorian tea party.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Next, create place cards for each guest. You can create these on the computer using clip art and fancy script fonts. If you're feeling particularly artistic, try using a calligraphy pen and pressed flowers. Place the cards in front of each table setting.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]><![CDATA[<h4>Food to Serve</h4>]]>Petite finger sandwiches with fillings like smoked salmon and cucumbers were a staple of every tea party. Offer your guests fresh fruit and cheese to nibble on. No tea party is complete without scones, crumpets, and jam.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Offer a selection of two or three teas. Traditionally, Earl Grey was served at tea parties but you can choose any variety you like. Serve tea in a china or silver teapot (never from the kettle). Round out the menu with classic petit fours, which are delicate bite-sized layer cakes covered with marzipan or fondant. You can probably find petit fours or a similar dessert at the local grocery store.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Serve all food on silver platters or cut glass trays-if you don't have these, pick up the plastic versions at the grocery store. Line each serving tray with paper lace doilies and remember to keep the food portions small. Over-indulgence was frowned upon in Margaret's era.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Decorate your house with flowers and play some ragtime or classical music to get your guests in the mood.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]><![CDATA[<h4>Conversation and Dress</h4>]]>Conversation should be kept light and lady-like. Ladies in Margaret's time always made an effort to be very polite. Gossip would certainly be frowned upon.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Encourage your friends to dress in traditional Victorian garb-big hats adorned with flowers, modest lacey dresses with high collars, and gloves would all be appropriate for your tea party. Try searching your local thrift store for dresses and hats-you might even come across a vintage tea set!</directions>
		<source>Photo Credit: Comstock Images/Getty</source>
	</craft>
	<craft>
		<template>1</template>
		<girlName>Abigail</girlName>
		<craftTitle>Sand Painting</craftTitle>
		<download>pdf/crafts/ArtsandCrafts_Abby_Sand_Painting.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/crafts/iStock_000000758820XSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/crafts/iStock_000000758820XBig.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description></description>
		<items>
			<item>Empty jars or plastic yogurt containers</item>
			<item>Powdered tempera paints in a variety of colors</item>
			<item>Sand (from the beach or playground)</item>
			<item>Paper, pencils, popsicle sticks, glue</item>
			<item>Plastic spoons, plastic or styrofoam tray</item>
			<item>Hair spray</item>
		</items>
		<directions><![CDATA[<p>Draw a picture on your paper (keep it simple).</p>
<p>Once the sketch is done, pour some sand into an empty jar or container, and mix a bit of tempera powder with the sand. Play around with the proportions of sand and tempera until you reach the vibrancy of color you want. Repeat this with a few different colors of tempera in different jars. Now your colored sand is ready to go!</p>
<p>To begin "painting," apply a thin, even layer of glue on one section of your drawing with a popsicle stick, and pour some colored sand onto the glue with a plastic spoon. Shake off the excess sand onto your tray (so you can re-use it). Repeat this process on each section of your drawing until all parts are bright and colorful.</p>
<p>Let the sand painting dry a few hours and spay with hair spray to seal.</p>]]></directions>
		<source></source>
	</craft>
	<craft>
		<template>1</template>
		<girlName>Abigail</girlName>
		<craftTitle>"Straw Hat" Making</craftTitle>
		<download>pdf/crafts/ArtsandCrafts_Abby_Straw_Hat.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/crafts/iStock_000003383818XSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/crafts/iStock_000003383818XBig.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description></description>
		<items>
			<item>Hat that resembles the shape of a straw hat</item>
			<item>Paper</item>
			<item>Scissors</item>
			<item>Glue</item>
		</items>
		<directions><![CDATA[<p>Cut the paper into long, thin strands. You'll need lots of them, enough to cover the entire circum- ference of the hat you're going off of. It might be necessary to glue some of the strands together to make them longer.</p>
<p>Weave the strands of paper together. Do this by crossing the edge of one paper under the edge of another strand and pulling gently until they hatch together. Do this with all the edges of the paper until you have a single, braided strand long enough to fit the bottom brim of your hat.</p>
<p>Glue the strand to the hat at this point. You'll probably need to glue the ends of the strands together, because it's going to be hard to weave them.</p>
<p>Repeat these steps until your hat is completely covered with strands and braids of paper. You may choose to accent the hat by adding extra strands of paper here and there.</p>
<p>Decorate the hat to give it a more realistic look. Paint it to the color of straw, if you wish. Add some grass or leaves to it to make it look natural. If you wish, purchase some strands of straw and attach them to the hat.</p>]]></directions>
		<source></source>
	</craft>
	
	<craft>
		<template>1</template>
		<girlName>Catherine</girlName>
		<craftTitle>Cornhusk Doll</craftTitle>
		<download>pdf/crafts/ArtsandCrafts_Catharine_Cornhusk_Doll.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/crafts/iStock_000008660759XSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/crafts/iStock_000008660759XBig.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description></description>
		<items>
			<item>Husks from 2 ears of corn (makes a 6" doll)</item>
			<item>Warm water</item>
			<item>Scissors</item>
			<item>String</item>
		</items>
		<directions><![CDATA[<p>Cut the end off of 2 ears of corn, and remove the husks and "hair." Dry it all in the sun for 1-3 days.</p>
<p>Soak the husks in warm water for 10 minutes before using. Cut the thin ends off. Bundle the thin end of 6 leaves around the "hair" (should be inside the body cylinder) and tie tightly with string. Peel the leaves down to form the head of the doll. The "hair" should sprout up in the middle.
</p><p>Tie the neck area with string. Braid 3 strips of leaf into a 6 inch piece for the arms. Braid 2 more of these 6 inches pieces, each of which will be used as a leg.</p>
<p>Put the arms under the tied neck by sticking it through the leaves of the body. Put a rolled up leaf inside the body cylinder, and then tie the waist area with string. Insert the legs. Secure by tying the bottoms of 2 body leaves between them, and tying a cornhusk around the waist. Then trim excess below the waist.</p>]]></directions>
		<source></source>
	</craft>
	<craft>
		<template>1</template>
		<girlName>Catherine</girlName>
		<craftTitle>Moccasins</craftTitle>
		<download>pdf/crafts/ArtsandCrafts_Catharine_Moccasins.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/crafts/iStock_000000198585XSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/crafts/iStock_000000198585XBig.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description></description>
		<items>
			<item>Buckskin or elkhide</item>
			<item>Heavy duty scissors</item>
			<item>Heavy duty thread</item>
			<item>Beads (optional)</item>
			<item>Awl</item>
		</items>
		<directions><![CDATA[<p>Purchase high quality buckskin or elkhide. It needs to be well tanned and thick, with no holes, no tears, or other flaws. It is best if it is smoked or waterproofed. Place your foot down on the hide and make a tracing of your foot with the awl.</p>
<p>Draw up the hide from the bottom and around the sides of your foot, mark with the awl, and cut the hide along the lines you have marked. Sew along a central seam starting with a puckered stitch at the toe and running along the upper instep.</p>
<p>Cut out a large "U-shaped" piece of hide that will serve as your vamp. Attach this vamp to the top of your moccasin from foot to toe.</p>
<p>Decorate your moccasins with beadwork. Most moccasins were plain for everyday use, but some moccasins, especially marriage moccasins, were often completely covered with beadwork.</p>]]></directions>
		<source></source>
	</craft>
	<craft>
		<template>1</template>
		<girlName>Patsy</girlName>
		<craftTitle>Basic Candles</craftTitle>
		<download>pdf/crafts/ArtsandCrafts_Patsy_Basic_Candles.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/crafts/iStock_000000377972XSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/crafts/iStock_000000377972XBig.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description></description>
		<items>
			<item>Several chunks of paraffin wax</item>
			<item>8-inch length of candlewick</item>
			<item>1 small empty can</item>
			<item>A saucepan</item>
		</items>
		<directions><![CDATA[<p>Fill the saucepan with about 2 inches of water and heat it over a low heat on the stove. Put a few chunks of paraffin wax into the can, and place the can into the water. Let the paraffin melt. Slowly lower the wick down into the liquid wax. Slowly lift the wick out. Hold it until the wax begins to cool and get solid. Repeat steps 4 and 5, over and over, until the candle is the size you want. Hang the candle by the wick end to cool. Trim the extra wick.</p>]]></directions>
		<source></source>
	</craft>
	<craft>
		<template>1</template>
		<girlName>Patsy</girlName>
		<craftTitle>Soap Making</craftTitle>
		<download>pdf/crafts/ArtsandCrafts_Patsy_Soap_Making.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/crafts/iStock_000005134843XSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/crafts/iStock_000005134843XBig.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description></description>
		<items>
			<item>Glycerin soap, clear or white (this only works with glycerin soap — do not substitute)</item>
			<item>Soap dye in colors of your choice</item>
			<item>Soap or candy molds</item>
			<item>Microwave-safe liquid measuring cup</item>
			<item>Spoon</item>
			<item>Popsicle stick or coffee stirrer</item>
			<item>Knife (adults only)</item>
		</items>
		<directions><![CDATA[<p>If you are using bars of soap, cut into three pieces. If you are using purchased glycerin blocks, cut off 2-3 pre-measured chunks. Put the glycerin soap into a measuring cup, and microwave according to package directions (or 20 seconds), then in 10-second intervals until melted.</p> <p>If you want colors, this is the time to add the dye. Add a few drops and stir with a spoon. If you want the color darker, simply add more dye.
Slowly pour the liquid soap into the mold. Set aside to harden for 45 minutes to an hour. Some soaps may harden sooner than others. Rinse out the measuring cup and repeat this process for other colors.</p>
<p>After the soap has cooled completely, pop it out of the molds. If you find this difficult, you can place the soap into the freezer for ten minutes and try again.</p>]]></directions>
		<source></source>
	</craft>
</crafts>