<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<crafts>
	<craft>
		<templateStyle>1</templateStyle>
		<girlName>Abigail</girlName>
		<craftTitle>Hand-Embroidered Monograms</craftTitle>
		<download>pdf/craft.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/recipes/toffeeSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/recipes/toffeeLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>A hand-embroidered handkerchief was a very common item in Abigail's day. It could be given to someone as a sign of affection or gratitude. You can also try embroidering some pillowcases or a t-shirt for a fun personalized item.</description>
		<items>
			<item>A word processing program</item>
			<item>A computer printer</item>
			<item>Linen, to be embroidered</item>
			<item>Tracing paper</item>
			<item>Pencils</item>
			<item>Pins</item>
			<item>Embroidery needles</item>
			<item>Scissors</item>
			<item>Embroidery floss</item>
			<item>Embroidery hoop</item>
			<item>An Iron</item>
		</items>
		<directions>Open your word processing program and type out your initials or first name. Go through the fonts on your computer and select a script-style font. You can play with different variations and sizes until you've developed a personalized monogram that suits your personality. When you've finished designing your monogram, print it out.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Using a piece of tracing paper and a pencil, carefully trace the letters of your monogram. Flip over the tracing paper and re-outline the letters, this time backwards. When finished, determine where you'd like your monogram to be on your linen. Transfer the monogram by securing the tracing paper with a pin and tracing the letters one more time. The letters should be faintly outlined on the fabric. Next, place your embroidery hoop around this area.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Choose the color of embroidery floss you wish to use and begin filling the area with satin stitches. Sew the satin stitch by bringing the needle up on one side of the outline of the first letter. Insert the needle down into the fabric directly across the outline of the letter. Point the needle down into the fabric right beside the point you brought up initially. Repeat this stitch to fill in the open spaces of each letter. Knot and cut your thread between letters. Change the color of your embroidery floss as desired.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>The satin stitch is a beautiful way to embroider a monogram but can be time consuming. If you're having trouble, you could also head to your local bookstore and pick up a beginner's guide to embroidery and follow the visual instructions.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>After you've finished satin stitching each letter, stitch an outline in either the same color embroidery floss or a contrasting one. Remove your embroidery hoop and press your design lightly with an iron.</directions>
		<source>http://www.ehow.com/how_4854186_embroider-letters-hand.html#ixzz0uEaw6S7L</source>
	</craft>
</crafts>