<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<recipes>
	<recipe>
		<girlName>Margaret</girlName>
		<recipeTitle>Toffee</recipeTitle>
		<download>pdf/recipe.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/recipes/toffeeSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/recipes/toffeeLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>Margaret would have bought her toffee in a penny candy store as a special treat. You could probably buy toffee at the store as well, but this homemade variety is a delicious way to impress your friends and satisfy your sweet tooth.</description>
		<ingredients>
			<ingredient>2 cups of butter</ingredient>
			<ingredient>2 cups of sugar</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/4 teaspoon of salt</ingredient>
			<ingredient>2 cups of semisweet chocolate chips</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 cup of finely chopped walnuts</ingredient>
		</ingredients>
		<servingsize>Makes 32 Servings</servingsize>
		<directions>In a large, heavy-bottomed saucepan, combine the butter, sugar, and salt. Cook over medium heat, stirring until the butter is melted. Allow the mixture to come to a boil. Continue to cook until the mixture becomes a dark amber color and the temperature has reached 285 degrees, as shown on your candy thermometer. If you don't have a candy thermometer, you can estimate.  285 degrees is the soft-crack stage. If you get a small bowl of cool water, you can drop a small drip of the candy mixture into the water. In the soft-crack stage, you should see the mixture solidify into threads that are flexible to the touch, not brittle. Stir occasionally. <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>While the toffee is cooking, cover a large baking sheet with aluminum foil or parchment paper. As soon as the toffee has reached the proper temperature, pour it into the prepared baking sheet. Sprinkle the chocolate chips over the top and let them set for a minute or two to soften. Spread the chocolate over the toffee in a thin layer once it has melted. Sprinkle the nuts over the chocolate and press in slightly. Putting a plastic bag over your hand will minimize the mess. <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Place the toffee in the refrigerator to chill until set. Break into pieces and store in an airtight container.</directions>
		<source>Photo Credit: Plush Studios/Getty</source>
	</recipe>
	
	<recipe>
		<girlName>Abigail</girlName>
		<recipeTitle>Dried Cranberries</recipeTitle>
		<download>pdf/recipe.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/recipes/DriedCranberriesSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/recipes/DriedCranberriesLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>To prepare for the long winter months, Abigail's family would have dried a variety of locally grown fruits and kept them cool and dry in barrels in the cellar of their home. Today, we're lucky enough to have fresh and exotic fruit all year round, thanks to airplanes and refrigeration.</description>
		<ingredients>
			<ingredient>1 (12 oz.) bag of cranberries</ingredient>
			<ingredient>2 quarts of boiling water</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 cup of sugar or corn syrup</ingredient>
		</ingredients>
		<servingsize>Makes 12 ounces</servingsize>
		<directions>In a bowl, pour boiling water over the cranberries. Let the cranberries sit in the water until the skins pop. Do not leave the berries in too long or else you'll end up with mush. Drain and coat the berries lightly with sugar or corn syrup.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Transfer the berries to a cookie sheet and place them in the freezer for two hours. Putting the cranberries in the freezer helps them dry out faster. Preheat your oven to 350 degrees. After ten minutes, turn off the oven. Place the cookie sheet with the berries in the oven and let sit overnight. This allows the berries to fully dehydrate.</directions>
		<source>Photo Credit: Dana Hoff/Getty</source>
	</recipe>
	<recipe>
		<girlName>Abigail</girlName>
		<recipeTitle>Mince Pie</recipeTitle>
		<download>pdf/recipe.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/recipes/MincePieSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/recipes/MincePieLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>This all-fruit version of a mince pie wouldn't have been exactly what Abigail and her family ate. Colonial mincemeat would have been prepared with a variety of fruit and spices as well as beef, venison, and even cow hearts. Our tastes today have changed, but this traditional pie still recalls some of the more pleasant colonial flavors.</description>
		<ingredients>
			<ingredient>1 (18 ounce) jar of prepared <![CDATA[<br />]]>mincemeat pie filling</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1-1/2 cups of chopped walnuts</ingredient>
			<ingredient>2 apples, peeled, cored, and chopped</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/2 cup of packed brown sugar</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/4 cup of apple juice</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 tablespoon of lemon juice</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 frozen store bought piecrust <![CDATA[<br />]]>(comes with two shells)</ingredient>
		</ingredients>
		<servingsize>Makes 8 Servings</servingsize>
		<directions>Combine mincemeat, walnuts, apples, brown sugar, apple juice, and lemon juice in a bowl. Cover and refrigerate overnight.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>The next day, preheat the oven to 425 degrees. Remove the piecrust from the freezer and allow to thaw. Place the bottom of the crust into a pie tin and spoon the filling into the shell. Top with the other crust and make slits to vent. Crimp the edges of the pie with a fork. Bake for 40 minutes or until golden brown.
</directions>
		<source>Photo Credit: Justin Lightley/Getty</source>
	</recipe>
	<recipe>
		<girlName>Abigail</girlName>
		<recipeTitle>Baked Apples</recipeTitle>
		<download>pdf/recipe.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/recipes/BakedApplesSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/recipes/BakedApplesLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>This yummy treat would have been available to Abigail during late summer and autumn, since that was the only time the apples were ripe and ready to pick.</description>
		<ingredients>
			<ingredient>4 large apples</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/4 cup of brown sugar</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 teaspoon of cinnamon</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/4cup of chopped pecans</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/4 cup of currants or <![CDATA[<br />]]>chopped raisins (optional)</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 tablespoon of butter</ingredient>
			<ingredient>3/4 cup of boiling water</ingredient>
		</ingredients>
		<servingsize>Makes 4 Servings</servingsize>
		<directions>Preheat the oven to 375 degrees. Wash the apples and remove the cores to 1/2 inch of the bottom of the apples. If you have an apple corer, use that. If not, use a paring knife to cut out the stem area, and then the core. Use a spoon to dig out any seeds. Make the holes about an inch wide.<![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>In a small bowl, combine the brown sugar, cinnamon, pecans, and currants/raisins (optional). Place the apples in an 8" by 8" baking pan. Stuff each apple with the sugar mixture. Top each apple with 1/4 tablespoon of butter.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Add the boiling water to the baking pan. Bake the apples for 30 to 40 minutes, until tender but not mushy. Remove the apples from the oven and baste the apples several times with the pan juice.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Serve warm with vanilla ice cream on the side.</directions>
		<source>Photo Credit: Getty Images</source>
	</recipe>
	<recipe>
		<girlName>Abigail</girlName>
		<recipeTitle>Fresh Mulled Cider</recipeTitle>
		<download>pdf/recipe.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/recipes/FreshMulledCiderSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/recipes/FreshMulledCiderLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>Abigail's cider would have been a much stronger concoction; traditional ciders were usually a very potent drink.</description>
		<ingredients>
			<ingredient>2 quarts of fresh apple cider</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 cup of maple syrup</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 stick of cinnamon</ingredient>
			<ingredient>A few whole cloves</ingredient>
			<ingredient>Lemon slices, cut in half, for garnish</ingredient>
		</ingredients>
		<servingsize>Makes 2 Quarts</servingsize>
		<directions>Combine the cider, syrup, cinnamon, and cloves in a large saucepan. Bring the cider just to a boil.  Remove the cloves and serve hot with lemon slices.</directions>
		<source>Photo Credits: Purestock/Getty</source>
	</recipe>
	<recipe>
		<girlName>Abigail</girlName>
		<recipeTitle>Ginger Snaps</recipeTitle>
		<download>pdf/recipe.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/recipes/GingerSnapsSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/recipes/GingerSnapsLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>You're lucky enough to be able to turn on your oven and bake anytime you like. When Abigail and her family wanted baked treats, they had to wake up very early in the morning in order to get their open-flame oven at the proper temperature. Baking was certainly an all day affair for Abigail.</description>
		<ingredients>
			<ingredient>2 cups of sifted all-purpose flour</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 tablespoon of ground ginger</ingredient>
			<ingredient>2 teaspoons of baking powder</ingredient>
			<ingredient>teaspoon of ground cinnamon</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/2 teaspoon of salt</ingredient>
			<ingredient>3/4 cup of shortening</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 cup of white sugar</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 egg</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/4 cup of dark molasses</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/3 cup of sugar</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/2 teaspoon of cinnamon</ingredient>
		</ingredients>
		<servingsize>Makes 2 Quarts</servingsize>
		<directions>Preheat the oven to 350 degrees. Sift the flour, ginger, baking soda, cinnamon, and salt into a mixing bowl. Stir the mixture to blend evenly and sift a second time into another bowl.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Place the shortening into a mixing bowl and beat until creamy. Gradually beat in the white sugar. Beat in the egg, and dark molasses. Sift 1/3 of the flour mixture into the shortening mixture; stir thoroughly to blend. Sift in the remaining flour mixture and mix together until soft dough forms. Pinch off small amounts of the dough and roll into 1-inch diameter balls. Roll each ball in cinnamon sugar and place about two inches apart on an ungreased baking sheet.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Bake in the oven until the tops are rounded and slightly cracked, about 10 minutes. Cool cookies on a wire rack and store in an airtight container. 
</directions>
		<source>Photo Credit: Rob Melnychuk/Getty</source>
	</recipe>
	<recipe>
		<girlName>Abigail</girlName>
		<recipeTitle>Fig Preserves</recipeTitle>
		<download>pdf/Recipes_Abby_Fig_Preserves.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/recipes/iStock_000007517041XSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/recipes/iStock_000007517041XBig.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description></description>
		<ingredients>
			<ingredient>16 cups of fresh figs</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 tablespoon of baking soda</ingredient>
			<ingredient>12 cups of boiling water</ingredient>
			<ingredient>8 cups of white sugar</ingredient>
			<ingredient>4 cups of water</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 lemon, sliced</ingredient>
		</ingredients>
		<servingsize></servingsize>
		<directions><![CDATA[<p>In a large mixing bowl place figs and sprinkle with baking soda. Pour the boiling water over the figs and soak for 1 hour.</p><p>
Drain figs and rinse thoroughly with cold water. In a large Dutch oven combine the sugar and the 4 cups of water; bring to a boil and cook for 10 minutes.</p><p>
Add the figs and lemon slices to the syrup in the Dutch oven and cook for 1 hour, stirring occasionally.</p><p>
Spoon figs into hot, sterilized jars and spoon syrup over figs, leaving 1/2 inch of headspace. Top jars with lids and screw bands on tightly. Process for 10 minutes in a hot water bath.<p>]]></directions>
		<source></source>
	</recipe>
	<recipe>
		<girlName>Abigail</girlName>
		<recipeTitle>Tea Biscuits</recipeTitle>
		<download>pdf/Recipes_Abby_Tea_Biscuits.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/recipes/iStock_000008207445XSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/recipes/iStock_000008207445XBig.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description></description>
		<ingredients>
			<ingredient>2 cups of all-purpose flour</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 tablespoon of baking powder</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 teaspoon of salt</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 tablespoon of white sugar</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/3 cup of shortening</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 cup of milk</ingredient>
		</ingredients>
		<servingsize></servingsize>
		<directions><![CDATA[<p>Preheat oven to 425 degrees F.</p>
In a large bowl, whisk together the flour, baking powder, salt, and sugar. Cut in the shortening until the mixture resembles coarse meal. Gradually stir in milk until dough pulls away from the side of the bowl.<p>
Turn out onto a floured surface, and knead 15 to 20 times. Pat or roll dough out to 1 inch thick. Cut biscuits with a large cutter or juice glass dipped in flour. Repeat until all dough is used. Brush off the excess flour, and place biscuits onto an ungreased baking sheet.</p>
<p>Bake for 13 to 15 minutes in the preheated oven, or until edges begin to brown.<p>]]></directions>
		<source></source>
	</recipe>
	<recipe>
		<girlName>Margaret</girlName>
		<recipeTitle>Smoked Salmon Tea Sandwiches</recipeTitle>
		<download>pdf/recipe.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/recipes/TeaSandwichesSmall_Salmon.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/recipes/TeaSandwichesLarge_Salmon.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>Even though we don't have traditional teatime here in the United States, tea sandwiches are a delicious snack any time of day.</description>
		<ingredients>
			<ingredient>1 cup of soft cream cheese</ingredient>
			<ingredient>20 slices of bread (any variety)</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/2 cup of capers</ingredient>
			<ingredient>12 ounces of thin sliced smoked salmon</ingredient>
			<ingredient>Juice of 1 lemon</ingredient>
			<ingredient>Black pepper, to taste</ingredient>
		</ingredients>
		<servingsize>Makes 40 Tea Sandwiches</servingsize>
		<directions>Spread the cream cheese on one side of each slice of bread. Arrange the smoked salmon on 10 of the bread slices and brush with lemon juice. Pepper each generously. Top with the other 10 slices and then remove the crusts and cut into fourths.
		</directions>
		<source>Photo Credit: Getty Images</source>
	</recipe>
	<recipe>
		<girlName>Margaret</girlName>
		<recipeTitle>Cucumber Tea Sandwiches</recipeTitle>
		<download>pdf/recipe.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/recipes/TeaSandwichesSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/recipes/TeaSandwichesLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>Even though we don't have traditional teatime here in the United States, tea sandwiches are a delicious snack any time of day.</description>
		<ingredients>
			<ingredient>1 large cucumber, peeled and <![CDATA[<br />]]>sliced very thin</ingredient>
			<ingredient>Salt</ingredient>
			<ingredient>3/4 cup of butter, softened</ingredient>
			<ingredient>2 teaspoons minced fresh garlic</ingredient>
			<ingredient>20 slices of bread (any variety)</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 tablespoon of lemon juice</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 tablespoon of olive oil</ingredient>
			<ingredient>Black pepper, to taste</ingredient>
		</ingredients>
		<servingsize>Makes 40 Tea Sandwiches </servingsize>
		<directions>Lightly salt the cucumber slices and place them in a colander to drain for 1 to 2 hours. Spread the butter and garlic and on one side of each slice of bread.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>In a small bowl, stir together the lemon juice, olive oil, and pepper. Add the cucumber slices, coating them well. Arrange the cucumber on 10 of the bread slices, top with the other 10 slices, remove the crusts, and quarter. Serve immediately. 
</directions>
		<source>Photo Credit: CaroleGomez/IStockphoto</source>
	</recipe>
	<recipe>
		<girlName>Margaret</girlName>
		<recipeTitle>Bangers and Mash</recipeTitle>
		<download>pdf/recipe.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/recipes/BangersandMashSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/recipes/BangersandMashLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>This English dish has been popular for nearly a century. Traditionally considered a working class dish, it is often found on pub menus throughout England. Although it was a favorite of Margaret's, she probably wouldn't have found it in the <![CDATA[<I>Titanic's</I>]]> luxurious first-class dining room.</description>
		<ingredients>
			<ingredient>8 large baking potatoes, peeled <![CDATA[<br />]]>and quartered</ingredient>
			<ingredient>2 teaspoons of butter, divided</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/2 cup of milk or more, as needed</ingredient>
			<ingredient>Salt and pepper, to taste</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1-1/2 pounds of beef sausage</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/2 onion, diced</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 package of dry brown gravy mix</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 cup of water or more, as needed</ingredient>
		</ingredients>
		<servingsize>Makes 8 Servings</servingsize>
		<directions>Preheat the oven to 350 degrees. Place the potatoes in a saucepan with enough water to cover them. Bring to a boil, and cook until tender, about 20 minutes. Drain and mash with 1 teaspoon of butter and milk until creamy. Season the mashed potatoes with salt and pepper.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>In a large skillet over medium heat, cook the sausage until heated through. Remove the cooked sausage from the pan and set aside. Add the remaining teaspoon of butter to the skillet and fry the onions over medium heat until tender. Mix together gravy mix and water as directed on the package and add to the skillet with the onions. Simmer, stirring constantly to form a thick gravy.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Pour half of the gravy into a square casserole dish so that it coats the bottom. Place the sausages in a layer over the gravy (you can butterfly the sausages if you wish) then pour the remaining gravy over them. Top the sausages with the prepared mashed potatoes. Bake uncovered for 20 minutes in a preheated oven, or until the potatoes are evenly browned.
</directions>
		<source>Photo Credit: Peter Cassidy/Getty</source>
	</recipe>
	<recipe>
		<girlName>Margaret</girlName>
		<recipeTitle>Vichyssoise or Cold Potato Soup</recipeTitle>
		<download>pdf/recipe.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/recipes/VichyssoiseSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/recipes/VichyssoiseLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>This delicious soup would have been considered very fashionable and high-class to the <![CDATA[<I>Titanic</I>]]> passengers. Louis Diat, a famous chef from the Ritz-Carlton in New York City, is often called the creator of the dish. He named it after his hometown in France, Vichy, for the soup was inspired by one of his mother's delicious recipes.</description>
		<ingredients>
			<ingredient>2 leeks, chopped</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 onion, chopped</ingredient>
			<ingredient>2 tablespoons of unsalted butter</ingredient>
			<ingredient>3/4 cup of thinly sliced potatoes</ingredient>
			<ingredient>2 1/3 cups of chicken stock</ingredient>
			<ingredient>Salt and black pepper, to taste</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 1/8 cup of heavy whipping cream</ingredient>
		</ingredients>
		<servingsize>Makes 5 Servings</servingsize>
		<directions>In a saucepan, cook the chopped leeks and onion in the butter. Do not allow them to brown. Add the potatoes and the chicken stock to the saucepan. Salt and pepper to taste. Bring to a boil and simmer gently for 30 minutes.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Remove the soup from the heat and puree it in a blender or food processor until smooth. Allow the soup to cool completely. Right before serving, stir in the heavy cream.</directions>
		<source>Photo Credit: Foodcollection/Getty</source>
	</recipe>
	<recipe>
		<girlName>Margaret</girlName>
		<recipeTitle>Hot Chocolate</recipeTitle>
		<download>pdf/recipe.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/recipes/HotChocolateSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/recipes/HotChocolateLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>This homemade hot chocolate is probably close to what Margaret drank in her grand <![CDATA[<I>Titanic</I>]]> stateroom. Lucky for us, we now have packaged hot chocolate mixes that are easily prepared in minutes. This recipe, however, would be an extra special treat on a chilly evening.</description>
		<ingredients>
			<ingredient>3 cups of milk</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/3 cup of semisweet chocolate, grated</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 tablespoon of sugar</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/2 teaspoon of ground cinnamon (optional)</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 egg</ingredient>
		</ingredients>
		<servingsize>Makes 2 Quarts</servingsize>
		<directions>Place the milk in a microwave-safe container and cook in the microwave on high for 2 minutes. Carefully remove the milk and mix in the chocolate, sugar, and cinnamon. In a separate bowl, whisk an egg until smooth. Add a tablespoon of the chocolate mixture to the egg and continue to whisk. Slowly add the egg mixture into the chocolate, spoonfuls at a time.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Return the mixture to the microwave and cook on high for three to four minutes until foamy (be mindful not to let the chocolate boil). Whisk the mixture until smooth and pour into 3 mugs. Garnish with a sprinkle of cinnamon, if desired.</directions>
		<source>Photo Credit: Kris Timken/Getty</source>
	</recipe>
	<recipe>
		<girlName>Mem</girlName>
		<recipeTitle>Hannah Potts Whipple's Ginger Cake</recipeTitle>
		<download>pdf/recipe.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/recipes/GingerCakeSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/recipes/GingerCakeLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>Mem and her family would consider this delicious cake an extra special treat. Spices were a luxury in the New World, as they had to be shipped from abroad. Supply ships arrived annually and only had a limited amount of spices onboard. Today, we have an endless amount of exotic spices available at our local grocery stores.</description>
		<ingredients>
			<ingredient>4 ounces of fresh ginger</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 cup of mild molasses</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 cup of sugar</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 cup of vegetable oil, preferably peanut</ingredient>
			<ingredient>2 1/2 cups of flour</ingredient>
			<ingredient>2 teaspoons of baking soda</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 teaspoon of ground cinnamon</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/2 teaspoon of ground cloves</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 teaspoon of black pepper</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 cup of water</ingredient>
			<ingredient>2 eggs, at room temperature</ingredient>
		</ingredients>
		<servingsize>Serves 10-12 people</servingsize>
		<directions>Preheat the oven to 350 degrees. Line a 9" by 3" cake pan with a circle of parchment paper. 
Peel, slice, and chop the ginger very fine with a knife. If it’s easier, use a grater. With a  mixer, mix together the molasses, sugar, and oil in a bowl. In another bowl, sift together the flour, baking soda, cinnamon, cloves, and black pepper.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Bring the water to a boil in a large saucepan. Remove the pan from heat. Mix the molasses mixture into the hot water. After this is combined, stir in the ginger.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Gradually whisk the dry ingredients into the saucepan. Add the eggs and continue mixing until everything is combined. Pour the batter into the prepared cake pan and bake for one hour. After an hour, test the cake by sticking a toothpick in the center. If the toothpick comes out clean, remove the cake from the oven. If your cake is very brown on top and the center is still gooey, cover the pan with a piece of tin foil and continue baking.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Let the cake cool for at least a half hour. Run a knife around the edges of the cake to loosen it from the pan. Gently remove the cake and peel away the parchment paper. 
</directions>
		<source>Photo Credit: travellinglight/IStockphoto</source>
	</recipe>
	<recipe>
		<girlName>Mem</girlName>
		<recipeTitle>Meat Pies</recipeTitle>
		<download>pdf/recipe.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/recipes/MeatPiesSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/recipes/MeatPiesLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>In Mem’s day, since there was no refrigeration, meats were often cured and salted to preserve them. Today, we can easily store meat in the freezer or head down to the grocery store when we’re craving something to eat.</description>
		<ingredients>
			<ingredient>1/2 pound of sausage</ingredient> 
			<ingredient>1/4 cup of chopped onion</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 celery stalk, diced</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 carrot, diced</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/2 cup of prepared mashed potatoes</ingredient>
			<ingredient>Salt and pepper, to taste</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 can of refrigerated biscuit dough</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 egg, beaten</ingredient>
		</ingredients>
		<servingsize>Makes 12 Small Pies</servingsize>
		<directions>Preheat your oven to 350 degrees. Brown the sausage, onion, celery, and carrot in a medium skillet. Add the mashed potatoes and season with salt and pepper.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Separate biscuits and flatten to make 3-inch rounds. Top each with a spoonful of meat filling. Pinch the edges to seal and brush with the beaten egg. Using a knife, make two small slits on the top. Place the little pies on a baking sheet and bake for 15 minutes or until golden brown. 
</directions>
		<source>Photo Credit: Kim Steele/Getty</source>
	</recipe>
	<recipe>
		<girlName>Mem</girlName>
		<recipeTitle>Indian Pudding</recipeTitle>
		<download>pdf/recipe.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/recipes/IndianPuddingSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/recipes/IndianPuddingLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>Preparing this pudding in Mem’s day would have been a very tedious task. She would have had to spend many hours toiling over an open flame brick oven with no thermometer. For less experienced cooks, this unreliable method often made puddings turn out less than delicious.</description>
		<ingredients>
			<ingredient>3 cups of whole milk</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 cup of heavy whipping cream</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/2 cup of yellow cornmeal</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/2 cup of light brown sugar, lightly packed</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/2 cup of molasses</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 teaspoon of salt</ingredient>
			<ingredient>2 teaspoons of ground cinnamon</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/4 teaspoon of ground nutmeg</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/4 teaspoon of ground cloves</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/4 teaspoon of ground ginger</ingredient>
			<ingredient>4 large eggs </ingredient>
			<ingredient>4 tablespoons of unsalted butter, <![CDATA[<br />]]>cut into four pieces</ingredient>
		</ingredients>
		<servingsize>Makes 8-16 Servings</servingsize>
		<directions>Preheat your oven to 275 degrees. Lightly grease an 8-cup souffle or baking dish <![CDATA[<br />]]>with butter.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]> 
In a medium-sized saucepan over medium-low heat, bring milk just to a boil. While the milk is heating, pour the cream into a medium large bowl. Then add the cornmeal, brown sugar, molasses, salt, cinnamon, nutmeg, cloves, and ginger. Add this mixture to the milk. Cook, whisking constantly, over medium-low heat until the pudding has thickened to the consistency of syrup (about 5 minutes). Remove from the heat.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>In a bowl, beat the eggs with whisk. Temper the eggs by adding 1/2 cup of the hot cornmeal mixture to the eggs while whisking rapidly. Vigorously whisk the rest of egg mixture into the cornmeal mixture. Add the butter, one piece at a time, stirring until melted.  Pour the mixture into the prepared souffle or baking dish and place the dish on a shallow baking pan on the center oven rack. Pour hot water into the baking pan so that it comes about 2/3 of the way up to the outsides of the souffle or baking dish.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Bake until the pudding is set, usually about 2 1/2 hours. Remove from the oven and remove the water bath. Let cool slightly. Serve warm with vanilla ice cream or <![CDATA[<br />]]>whipped cream. 
</directions>
		<source>Photo Credit: Brian Hagiwara/Foodpix/Getty Images</source>
	</recipe>
	<recipe>
		<girlName>Piper</girlName>
		<recipeTitle>WWII Oatmeal Molasses Cookies</recipeTitle>
		<download>pdf/recipe.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/recipes/OatmealMolassesCookieSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/recipes/OatmealMolassesCookieLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>Since sugar was rationed during the war, clever cooks replaced all the brown sugar in their recipes with molasses. White sugar was still hard to come by but brown sugar was nearly impossible to find. It was a great switch, though—people still make molasses cookies without the ration! Try and see what you think.</description>
		<ingredients>
			<ingredient>2 cups of all-purpose flour</ingredient>
			<ingredient>3/4 cup of butter</ingredient> 
			<ingredient>2 cups of oatmeal</ingredient>
			<ingredient>2 eggs, beaten</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 teaspoon of baking soda</ingredient> 
			<ingredient>5 tablespoons of light molasses</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 teaspoon of baking powder</ingredient> 
			<ingredient>2 teaspoons of vanilla extract</ingredient> 
			<ingredient>1 teaspoon of salt</ingredient> 
			<ingredient>1 cup of sugar</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/2 cup of chopped walnuts (optional)</ingredient> 
			<ingredient>1/2 cup of raisins (optional)</ingredient>
		</ingredients>
		<servingsize></servingsize>
		<directions>Preheat oven to 350 degrees. In a large bowl, stir together the flour, oatmeal, baking soda, baking powder and salt. In another large bowl, beat the sugar with the shortening until smooth and creamy; mix in beaten eggs, molasses, and vanilla.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Gradually mix in the dry ingredients. Stir in walnuts and raisins, if desired. Drop by teaspoonfuls onto ungreased baking sheets. Bake for 10-12 minutes, or until slightly browned. Allow cookies to cool on baking sheet for 5 minutes before removing to a wire rack to cool completely.
		</directions>
		<source>Photo Credit: Justin Bernhaul/Getty</source>
	</recipe>
	<recipe>
		<girlName>Piper</girlName>
		<recipeTitle>Margie's Meatloaf</recipeTitle>
		<download>pdf/recipe.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/recipes/MargiesMeatloafSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/recipes/MargiesMeatloafLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>Meatloaf is almost as American as apple pie. This traditional dinner staple has been popular for the better part of a century and pleases hungry folks all around the country. Remember, there was a sugar ration in Piper’s day, she would’ve had to eliminate the brown sugar topping.</description>
		<ingredients>
			<ingredient>1 1/2 pounds of ground beef</ingredient> 
			<ingredient>1 egg</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 onion, chopped</ingredient> 
			<ingredient>1 cup of milk</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 cup of dried breadcrumbs</ingredient> 
			<ingredient>Salt and pepper, to taste</ingredient>
			<ingredient>2 tablespoons of brown sugar</ingredient> 
			<ingredient>2 tablespoons of mustard</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/3 cup of ketchup</ingredient>
		</ingredients>
		<servingsize></servingsize>
		<directions>Preheat oven to 350. In a large bowl, combine the beef, egg, onion, milk and breadcrumbs. Season with salt and pepper to taste and place in a lightly greased 5x9" loaf pan, or form into a loaf and place in a lightly greased 9x13" baking dish. In a separate small bowl, combine the brown sugar, mustard and ketchup. Mix well and pour over the meatloaf. Bake for 1 hour.
	</directions>
		<source>Photo Credit: Christina Peters/Getty</source>
	</recipe>
	<recipe>
		<girlName>Piper</girlName>
		<recipeTitle>Crab Louie</recipeTitle>
		<download>pdf/recipe.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/recipes/CrabLouieSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/recipes/CrabLouieLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>Piper ordered this salad as a special treat on her birthday and now you can make it at home. Crab Louie salads were extremely popular restaurant fare during the beginning and middle of the 20th century. They’ve since faded in popularity but are still delicious.</description>
		<ingredients>
			<ingredient>1 pint of mayonnaise</ingredient> 
			<ingredient>1/2 pint of tomato ketchup</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 tablespoon finely chopped <![CDATA[<br />]]>green bell pepper</ingredient>
			<ingredient>Worcestershire sauce, to taste</ingredient>
			<ingredient>Salt and pepper, to taste</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 head of iceberg lettuce, chopped</ingredient> 
			<ingredient>8 to 12 ounces of fresh picked <![CDATA[<br />]]>Dungeness crabmeat</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 avocado, peeled, pitted, and <![CDATA[<br />]]>thinly sliced lengthwise</ingredient> 
			<ingredient>3 tomatoes, quartered</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/2 pound of asparagus spears, cooked</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 hard boiled egg, chopped (optional)</ingredient>
			<ingredient>4 tablespoons of unsalted butter, <![CDATA[<br />]]>cut into four pieces</ingredient>
		</ingredients>
		<servingsize></servingsize>
		<directions>To make dressing, mix together mayonnaise, ketchup, peppers, Worcestershire sauce, and salt and pepper.  <![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>Make a bed of iceberg lettuce on a large plate. Top with crab, avocado, tomatoes, and asparagus. Drizzle with Louie dressing, garnish with the hard-boiled egg (optional), serve and enjoy!
	</directions>	 		  
	<source>Photo Credit: Jodi Kelly/ iStockphoto</source>
	</recipe>
	<recipe>
		<girlName>Piper</girlName>
		<recipeTitle>Shirley Temple</recipeTitle>
		<download>pdf/recipe.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/recipes/ShirleyTempleSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/recipes/ShirleyTempleLarge.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description>This yummy drink is named after the child star, Shirley Temple. She was extremely popular during the 1930s and 1940s and Piper would have seen all of her movies. Why not rent one of her classics (A Little Princess, Heidi, or Curly Top) and sip on one of these delicious drinks?</description>
		<ingredients>
			<ingredient>1/4 cup of ginger ale or Sprite</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 1/2 tablespoons of grenadine syrup</ingredient>
			<ingredient>Maraschino cherries, for garnish</ingredient>
		</ingredients>
		<servingsize> 1 serving</servingsize>
		<directions>In a glass, over ice, combine ginger ale and grenadine. Stir well and garnish with maraschino cherries.</directions>
		<source>Photo Credit: pjohnson1/IStockphoto</source>
	</recipe>

<recipe>
		<girlName>Patsy</girlName>
		<recipeTitle>Hard Gingerbread</recipeTitle>
		<download>pdf/recipe.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/recipes/iStock_000008250696XSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/recipes/iStock_000008250696XBig.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description></description>
		<ingredients>
			<ingredient>1/2 pound of butter</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 pound of flour</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/2 pound of sugar</ingredient>
			<ingredient>2 tablespoons of ginger</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 tablespoon of rosewater</ingredient>
		</ingredients>
		<servingsize></servingsize>
		<directions>Preheat the oven to 350°F. In a bowl, combine the butter with the flour. Then add the sugar, ginger, and rosewater. Stir until well mixed. Roll out the dough and bake in a flat pan in the oven. It will take about half an hour to bake.</directions>
		<source></source>
	</recipe>

<recipe>
		<girlName>Patsy</girlName>
		<recipeTitle>Sweet Potato Coffee</recipeTitle>
		<download>pdf/Recipes_Patsy_Sweet_Potato_Coffee.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/recipes/iStock_000004270930XSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/recipes/iStock_000004270930XBig.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description></description>
		<ingredients>
			<ingredient>2 sweet potatoes, peeled and sliced thin.</ingredient>
		</ingredients>
		<servingsize></servingsize>
		<directions>Preheat the oven to 350°F. Lay out the sweet potato slices on a cookie sheet and place in the oven. Allow the sweet potatoes to completely dry out in the oven for a few hours.<![CDATA[<br /><br />]]>
After the potatoes are dried, take them out and place the slices in a coffee grinder. Three table- spoons of ground sweet potato "coffee" will make 5-6 cups of coffee.</directions>
		<source></source>
	</recipe>
	<recipe>
		<girlName>Catherine</girlName>
		<recipeTitle>Pumpkin Pudding</recipeTitle>
		<download>pdf/Recipes_Catharine_Pumpkin_Pudding.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/recipes/iStock_000014428169XSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/recipes/iStock_000014428169XBig.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description></description>
		<ingredients>
			<ingredient>1 15 ounce can of solid pack pumpkin</ingredient>
			<ingredient>pumpkin</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 12 fluid ounce can of evaporated milk</ingredient>
			<ingredient>3/4 cup of white sugar</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/2 cup of biscuit/baking mix</ingredient>
			<ingredient>2 eggs, beaten</ingredient>
			<ingredient>2 tablespoons of butter or margarine, melted</ingredient>
			<ingredient>2 1/2 teaspoons of pumpkin pie spice</ingredient>
			<ingredient>2 teaspoons of vanilla extract</ingredient>
			<ingredient>Whipped Topping (optional)</ingredient>
		</ingredients>
		<servingsize></servingsize>
		<directions>In a large bowl, combine the first eight ingredients. Transfer to a slow cooker coated with nonstick cooking spray. Cover and cook on low for 6-7 hours or until a thermometer reads 160 degrees. Serve in bowls with whipped topping if desired.</directions>
		<source></source>
	</recipe>
	<recipe>
		<girlName>Catherine</girlName>
		<recipeTitle>Corncakes</recipeTitle>
		<download>pdf/Recipes_Catharine_Corncakes.pdf</download>
		<imageSmall>images/recipes/iStock_000012998026XSmall.jpg</imageSmall>
		<imageLarge>images/recipes/iStock_000012998026XBig.jpg</imageLarge>
		<description></description>
		<ingredients>
			<ingredient>2 cups of cornmeal</ingredient>
			<ingredient>4 tablespoons of flour</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 tablespoon of baking powder</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1 teaspoon salt</ingredient>
			<ingredient>2 eggs</ingredient>
			<ingredient>2 cups of whole milk</ingredient>
			<ingredient>1/4 cups of oil</ingredient>
		</ingredients>
		<servingsize></servingsize>
		<directions><![CDATA[Measure and sift dry ingredients together into a large bowl. Make a well in the center. Mix the eggs, milk and oil together. Pour into the well and stir until combined. Pour batter onto an oiled griddle until bubbles form and bottoms are golden brown. Turn and continue cooking until browned on the other side. Remove from griddle and serve hot.
		]]></directions>
		<source></source>
	</recipe>
</recipes>